I’m Frank Elavsky and this is my latest project:
Data Navigator: an accessibility-centered data
navigation toolkit. This work was in collaboration
with Lucas Nadolskis and Dominik Moritz.
This is a bar chart. Let’s say it’s interactive.
I might be able to hover using
a mouse to see a tooltip.
Or perhaps I can even click the
bars in order to do something
like open some data or filter or go to a webpage.
But data visualizations often only have mouse
support. Sometimes limited touch support.
Support for screen readers or
other assistive technologies
and input modalities pretty much
doesn’t exist in most toolkits.
Making data visualizations accessible for people
with disabilities is, of course, important. But
how do we get there? How can we realize this goal?
Research on what users with disabilities want and
accessibility standards and guidelines aren’t
enough. The toolkits and ecosystems we use to
craft data visualizations must give visualization
designers and developers the ability to follow
best practices and explore new design ideas.
But as it stands, toolkits have a ways to go.
Access for many assistive technologies is
a navigation problem. And most toolkits out
there offer virtually nothing to developers
to design and control navigation experiences.
For example, screen readers, which are typically
used by blind and low vision users, navigate.
And other devices may rely on keyboard, voice,
or gesture inputs. These typically have discrete
or direct navigation controls are may be used by
people with motor or dexterity disabilities. Some
of these devices have been around a long time.
For example, shown is a wheelchair user who is
using a sip and puff device from the 1960s. This
controls and navigates a computer using breathing
patterns. These devices are still used today.
And what about the future of input devices?
Future and fabricated interfaces in particular
are a subject of study in accessibility
contexts such as physical therapy,
rehabilitation, working with children
with disabilities, and the elderly.
One particular study that I love from 2014
used objects that could be found in a kitchen,
primarily produce, to create a tangible
interface in an aging community setting.
Visualization toolkits currently cannot handle the
assistive technologies of the
past, let alone the future.
So I would like to present our project, Data
Navigator. It is a system that provides an
entirely new accessibility substrate.
Data navigator adds navigable structure,
input handling, and rendering
capabilities to data visualizations.
We intend for our system to
work in tandem with toolkits,
allowing them to provide robust accessibility
capabilities downstream to their users.
I’ll give a brief demo. This is a png chart
from highcharts. This chart isn’t interactive,
it is literally just pixels, but I used
data navigator to make it navigable and
interactive. I am first navigating
this chart using a keyboard. The title, axes,
legend, and all the bars in the bar chart
are now accessible thanks to Data Navigator.
And Data navigator’s renderer also adds semantics
and text descriptions for screen readers.
Using our input handling subsystem I can
navigate by swiping in various
directions on a touch device,
And even gesture with my hands using
a simple gesture detection model.
Voice commands and typed text also work,
which are in our live demo but not shown
here. And we also wanted to validate and test future interfaces so we
replicated version of Rogers et al’s fabricated
produce-based input system, just to show
the power of Data Navigator.
You’re welcome to explore our live demo yourself
too. You can find the link in our paper.
So data navigator is actually built on a
graph structure. A graph is formed out of
nodes and edges. These are our primitive elements.
And nodes and edges can, of course, be used to
represent almost every other data structure:
they can create tables, lists, and hierarchies.
But they also can be used to represent network
graphs, infographic and mathematical diagrams,
flows, spatial structures like maps, and even
custom paths through a visualization's story.
Nodes can be virtually anything,
structurally: individual data points,
groups of data points, or even information that
isn't originally part of a dataset like a title,
axis label, visual feature, or annotation.
Our edges, which have navigation rules, can
also be anything. Our rules are abstract!
So left, right, up down, or even
a rule like Legend can exist on an
edge. Our rules are whatever
makes sense for the visual.
Lastly, rendering is an issue for
toolkits. As an example of this,
the charting library Highcharts has both
SVG and raster based rendering options,
like from our demo earlier. You can render the
exact same visualization using either method.
But rendering using SVG is typically much more
accessible while raster rendering is much faster.
This means toolkit developers are in a bad place:
offering a more efficient technology
that excludes people with disabilities.
However, Data Navigator’s rendering
subsystem creates an accessible HTML layer,
and provides full control to developers
over the styling and semantics so it
can integrate seamlessly into the visual’s
design. This HTML layer can be placed over
any graphic. Our whole subsystem lazy-loads each
element, which means that it is really fast too.
In our paper we added data navigator to
Vega-lite’s canvas rendering programmatically.
This allowed us to automatically add navigable
accessibility to quite a lot of basic visualization
that vega-lite renders. And the best part
is that our system is quite lightweight,
initializing in 10 milliseconds for a
chart with 20,000 data points. That’s fast.
And data navigator can be used for exploring
novel and unaddressed navigation designs. Our
blind co-author and co-designer Lucas Nadolskis
and I designed schemas for navigating vector
and set diagrams and made prototypes using
Data Navigator. Check out the paper for more.
So what’s next? Well, we believe that our
technical contribution opens up several
lines of co-design and human studies work.
What do users whose disabilities have been
unaddressed by current literature
want and need from an accessible,
interactive visualization experience? We should
work to establish ideal patterns for use,
especially for visualization
types that are not well studied.
And our most immediate future
work is towards practical aims:
we intend to provide a user interface
for building navigation structures.
Users could create nodes, connect them with edges,
and declare navigation rules.
We hope this will help teams
such as data journalists who might build
charts and graphs that need design finesse
really control their accessible navigation
experience without having to write code.
And we’re looking for collaborations! Are you
building a charting library or are part of a team,
such as a news organization, that puts out charts
and graphs? I’d love to talk. Please reach out.
Thank you.